<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2.  Equations of State on Cryo-Rocket.com</title>
    <link>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2.  Equations of State on Cryo-Rocket.com</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.1-background/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.1-background/</guid>
      <description>MathJax = { tex: {inlineMath: [[&#39;$&#39;, &#39;$&#39;], [&#39;\\(&#39;, &#39;\\)&#39;]]} };  Equations of State The previous section tracked the enthalpy of the propellants as they flowed through the components of the engine. But what exactly is enthalpy? And what does it have to do with an equation of state? Enthalpy is not as intuitive to understand as the pressure and temperature of a fluid. Mathematically, enthalpy is defined as follows:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.2-hydrogen-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.2-hydrogen-model/</guid>
      <description>MathJax = { tex: {inlineMath: [[&#39;$&#39;, &#39;$&#39;], [&#39;\\(&#39;, &#39;\\)&#39;]]} };  Hydrogen Phase Diagram As shown in the previous section, the reduced Helmholtz equation of state can be broken into two components, one modeling ideal gas effects ($\alpha^0$), and the other corresponding to the residual contribution from intermolecular forces ($\alpha^r$). This equation of state allows for construction of a phase diagram that is more nuanced than the “four quadrant” model described in Section 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.3-oxygen-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.3-oxygen-model/</guid>
      <description>MathJax = { tex: {inlineMath: [[&#39;$&#39;, &#39;$&#39;], [&#39;\\(&#39;, &#39;\\)&#39;]]} };  Oxygen Phase Diagram The oxygen phase diagram displays similar trends to those discussed on the hydrogen phase diagram in the previous section. As shown below in Figures 2.3.1. and 2.3.2, a discontinuity in the density field is clearly visible along the saturation line, as expected due to the simultaneous existence of both liquid and gaseous oxygen. This discontinuity gradually smooths out along the pseudo-boiling line above the critical point.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.4-combustion-products/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.4-combustion-products/</guid>
      <description>MathJax = { tex: {inlineMath: [[&#39;$&#39;, &#39;$&#39;], [&#39;\\(&#39;, &#39;\\)&#39;]]} };  Combustion Products The Helmholtz correlations in Sections 2.2 and 2.3 were designed to model hydrogen and oxygen at relatively low temperatures where intermolecular forces cannot be neglected. The hydrogen correlation is accurate within the following limits:[11]
14 K 7 MPa The oxygen model is even further restricted:[12]
54 K 0 MPa Propellant temperatures remain in this range as they flow through this SSME’s network of pumps and turbines (refer to Sections 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.5-enthalpy-revisited/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.5-enthalpy-revisited/</guid>
      <description>MathJax = { tex: {inlineMath: [[&#39;$&#39;, &#39;$&#39;], [&#39;\\(&#39;, &#39;\\)&#39;]]} };  Enthalpy Revisited It is interesting to note that the empirical correlation for enthalpy shown in Section 2.4 is a function of temperature alone:
(2.4.2) $$ \frac{h}{R_u\,T} = a_1+a_2\frac{T}{2}\,T+a_3\frac{T^2}{3}+a_4\frac{T^3}{4}+a_5\frac{T^4}{5}+b_1\,T \,\,\,\,\,\text{[J/mol]} $$ This is surprising, especially since in Section 2.1 enthalpy was defined as follows:
(2.1.1) $ h=u+\frac{P}{\rho} $ Pressure and density both clearly play a role in this equation, which is applicable to both liquids and gasses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.6-transport-properties/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bbbrady1.github.io/equation-of-state/2.6-transport-properties/</guid>
      <description>MathJax = { tex: {inlineMath: [[&#39;$&#39;, &#39;$&#39;], [&#39;\\(&#39;, &#39;\\)&#39;]]} };  Transport Properties The equations of state discussed in the previous sections enabled us to calculate the thermodynamic properties of hydrogen, oxygen, and their associated combustion products. We now direct our attention to the transport properties of these propellants. Transport properties describe how a fluid disperses energy. There are two properties of interest: thermal conductivity and viscosity. Thermal conductivity describes a fluid’s ability to transfer heat via conduction.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
